<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The prologue and epilogue to the new comedy, called Sir Courtly Nice, or, It cannot be</title>
            <author>Crown, Mr. (John), 1640?-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7399</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30975</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11752414</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11752414</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48609</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35292)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48609)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1483:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The prologue and epilogue to the new comedy, called Sir Courtly Nice, or, It cannot be</title>
                  <author>Crown, Mr. (John), 1640?-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Benskins ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Crowne by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48609:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48609:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PROLOGUE AND EPILOGUE To the NEW COMEDY, CALLED, Sir Courtly Nice, or, It Cannot be.</head>
            <div type="prologue">
               <head>The PROLOGUE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat are the Charms by which theſe happy Iſles,</l>
                  <l>Have gain'd Heavens brighteſt, and Eternal Smiles?</l>
                  <l>What Nation upon Earth beſides our own,</l>
                  <l>But by a loſs like ours had been undone?</l>
                  <l>Ten Ages ſcarce ſuch Royal worth diſplay,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>England</hi> Loſt, and Found, in one ſtrange day.</l>
                  <l>One hour in Sorrow and Confuſion hurl'd,</l>
                  <l>And yet the next the Envy of the World.</l>
                  <l>Nay, we are Bleſt in Spite of us, 'tis known,</l>
                  <l>Heavens Choice for us, was better than our own.</l>
                  <l>To ſtop the Bleſſings that o'reflow this day,</l>
                  <l>What heaps of Rogues we pil'd up in the way?</l>
                  <l>We choſe fit Tools againſt all good to ſtrive,</l>
                  <l>The Sawcieſt, Lewdeſt Proteſtants alive.</l>
                  <l>They wou'd have form'd a Bleſſed Church indeed,</l>
                  <l>Upon a Turn-Coat Doctors Lying Creed;</l>
                  <l>To know if e're he took Degree is hard,</l>
                  <l>'Tis thought he'l have one in the <hi>Palace-Yard.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plot-Swallowers</hi> ſure, will Drink no more Stuff down,</l>
                  <l>From that foul Pitcher, when his Ears are gone.</l>
                  <l>Let us Rely on Conſcience, not on Cheats,</l>
                  <l>On Heavens Wiſdom, not State-Juglers Feats.</l>
                  <l>How greatly Heaven has our loſs ſupplyed?</l>
                  <l>'Tis no ſmall Vertue Heals a Wound ſo wide:</l>
                  <l>Nay, in ſo little time to Rear our Head,</l>
                  <l>To our own Wonder, and our Neighbours dread.</l>
                  <l>They ſee that Valour Crown'd with Regal Power,</l>
                  <l>They have oft ſeen with Lawrels Crown'd before.</l>
                  <l>Verſe is too Narrow for ſo great a Name;</l>
                  <l>Far ſounding Seas hourly repeat his Fame.</l>
                  <l>Our Neighbours Vanquiſh'd Fleets oft wafted o're,</l>
                  <l>His Name to theirs, and many a Trembing Shore.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:48609:2"/>
                  <l>And we may go by his great Conduct Lead,</l>
                  <l>As far in Fame as our Fore-Fathers did.</l>
                  <l>At Home, he milder ways to Glory choſe;</l>
                  <l>God-like, by Patience, he Subdued his Foes:</l>
                  <l>Now they, and their Deſigns are Ruin'd all,</l>
                  <l>Beneath their fallen accurſt Excluding Wall:</l>
                  <l>Theſe are not all the Bleſſings of this Iſle,</l>
                  <l>Heaven on our Nation in a Queen doth Smile,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Vertues, Grac'd by Beauty, ſhine ſo bright,</l>
                  <l>All the Fair Sex to Vertue ſhe'l Invite,</l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And all our Clouds turn to a Glorious day,</l>
                     <l>By this Illuſtrious pairs United Ray,</l>
                     <l>Who both Reform and Grace us by their Sway.</l>
                  </lg>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <head>The EPILOGUE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO plead for Freedome in ſo free a time,</l>
                  <l>May ſeem Impertinent, if not a Crime.</l>
                  <l>The Circling Sea, gives Limits to our Shores,</l>
                  <l>But nothing bounds our Rabble, Wives, or Whores.</l>
                  <l>In Spite of all Indulgent Sway can do,</l>
                  <l>Our Croud, their Luſt of Faction will perſue,</l>
                  <l>And either Sex will to their Joys go on,</l>
                  <l>Scorning all ills to Honour, Purſe, or Bone.</l>
                  <l>Nay, Parents now, not only can endure</l>
                  <l>Their Childrens Faults, but which is worſe, procure,</l>
                  <l>Of Old, Proud Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her, full of Parent Sway,</l>
                  <l>Kept Miſs a Vaſſal to her work all day;</l>
                  <l>And to the Wooing Spark, Miſs was not brought,</l>
                  <l>But ſome fine Golden thing, her Needle wrought.</l>
                  <l>Now you ſhall meet Young Lady and her Mother,</l>
                  <l>Rambling in <hi>Hackney-Coaches,</hi> Maſqu'd together.</l>
                  <l>Yes, and to Speak the Truth, to work they go,</l>
                  <l>Fine work, but ſuch as they will never ſhow;</l>
                  <l>Except ſome Net to draw a Fool to Wed,</l>
                  <l>And then he finds Miſs rare at work — a Bed.</l>
                  <l>Nay, we have gotten other Schools of late,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Maſquerades,</hi> and the <hi>Jews Chocolate.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There Fowler like, a watching Gallant pores,</l>
                     <l>Behind his Glove, to get a Shot at Whores,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Coach and Bones comes Ratling to the Dores.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <l>Nearer he creeps, diſcharges ſome kind words,</l>
                  <l>And off he carries ſtreight the wounded Birds.</l>
                  <l>Another Gallant waits in the great Room,</l>
                  <l>Till a New Cargazon of Strumpets come;</l>
                  <l>And there with his own Face he Treats his Eyes;</l>
                  <l>What need he ſee, he can Act Comedies?</l>
                  <l>There by four Glaſſes plac'd, as for the nonce,</l>
                  <l>Sir Sparkiſh Acts four Coxcombs all at once.</l>
                  <l>Our Galleries were finely us'd of late,</l>
                  <l>Where Rooſting Maſques ſate Cackling for a Mate;</l>
                  <l>They came not to ſee Plays, but Act their own,</l>
                  <l>And had throng'd Audiences when we had none:</l>
                  <l>Both Pit and Gallery was a Strumpet Fair,</l>
                  <l>Where Higling Whores, Sold Rotten Pumpions dear.</l>
                  <l>This Comedy throws all this Leudneſs down,</l>
                  <l>For Vertuous Liberty it pleads alone;</l>
                  <l>Promotes the Stage toth' ends at firſt deſign'd,</l>
                  <l>At once to Profit and Delight the Mind.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> Tho. Benskin <hi>at the Corner Shop i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Little-Lincolns-Inn-Fields. 1685.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48609:2"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
